Hey, focus ho, everyone! Welcome to the first day of the rest
of your lives.
Welcome to the first day of what I hope will be a
wonderful seven and a half years together as we start a new
cycle of going through ש"ס. Shas. Please mark on your calendars January
5th, 2020 for our next סיום הש"ס. Siyum HaShas. Oh, great. And
I thought it was January 4th. What? It's wonderful. I know. The
סיום's Siyum on the 5th. Now, I also want to welcome, of
course, it's a wonderful group here and I hope many of you
are here not just for today but will decide to stay and,
in particular, I want to welcome my family's here today because today
is also a very special day. It is ט"ו באב Tu B'Av
and it is my son איתנו's Eitano בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah day.
איתנו Eitano and I love learning גמרא Gemara together and we thought
it would be so lovely for him and for everybody to come.
And I do want to say that one of the beautiful things
about learning דף Daf is that it really
unifies Jews who are engaged in this process all over the world.
Everybody is on the same page on any given day. But in
addition to sort of unifying people wherever they might be, also, of
course, part of learning גמרא Gemara is the sense of tradition and
continuity and from generation to generation. And I've been teaching דף Daf
from this ש"ס Shas that has been handed down to me from
my grandfather,
who, as I understand, who כתריאל Kasriel here, כתריאל's Kasriel named after,
and that also makes it very special. And איתנו Eitano is named
after my mother-in-law, עליה השלום, Aleha HaShalom, whose יארצייט Yahrtzeit is actually
coming up in just a few weeks. So it really is, I'm
sure that both of them are looking down and they're really getting
a tremendous amount of נחת Nachas and we should just all be
זוכה zoche to continue to learn גמרא Gemara amongst ourselves and to
pass it down, continue the tradition and pass it down to future
generations. And with that we will begin. So let's take a look.
ברכות דף ב עמוד א. Brachos Daf Bais Amud Aleph. Everyone have
a גמרא? Gemara? מאימתי? Me'aimasai? There are גמרות Gemaras here if you
look on. מאימתי, Me'aimasai, we'll try to get more. מאימתי קורין את
שמע בערבין? Me'aimasai korin es Shema be'arvin? When do you begin, when
do you start, when do you say the שמע Shema in the
evening? משעה שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול בתרומתן. Mishesha hakohanim nichnasin leechol betrumasan.
From the time that the כהנים Kohanim enter in, meaning presumably enter
in from the field to the city, they're going to eat their
תרומה. Terumah. Often the כהנים Kohanim would go to the מקוה Mikvah
if they became טמא, tamei, impure that day. They'd go to the
מקוה. Mikvah. The מקוה Mikvah might be located somewhat on the outskirts.
They'd go near the end of the day and they would be
able to eat תרומה Terumah when the at nightfall. We'll describe, we'll
define nightfall in a minute. So when they come in to eat
their תרומה, Terumah, that is when you can begin saying the evening
שמע. Shema. עד סוף האשמורה הראשונה. Ad sof ha'ashmurah harishonah. Until the
end of the first watch. The night was divided into watches and
we'll discuss that. Not watch like a wristwatch, watch
like a watchers of a guards of a city. And it was
divided into what was called watches and until the end of the
first watch you could say the שמע. Shema. דברי רבי אליעזר. Divrei
Rabbi Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. וחכמים אומרים. Vachachamim
omrim. And we'll find out that the first watch was about three
hours into the night, maybe four hours into the night. וחכמים אומרים,
Vachachamim omrim, the sages say, עד חצות, ad chatzos, until midnight. So
assume a day that sunrise is six and sunset is six, so
the first position will have it till 9 or 10 PM and
the חכמים Chachamim will say until midnight you can say it. רבן
גמליאל אומר, Rabban Gamliel omer, עד שיעלה עמוד השחר, ad sheya'aleh amud
hashachar, until the morning star rises, which is normally assumed to be
about 72 minutes before sunrise. So you can pretty much say it
throughout the night up until not sunrise but up until the day
begins to break, until the morning star. So here is a debate
not when you start, that we'll see a discussion in the גמרא,
Gemara, but till how long can you go. Now, what is this
debate about? The גמרא Gemara sort of alludes to it. רש"י, Rashi,
not this דף, daf, the next דף, daf, says very simply, it
is a question about how you read the verse that actually is
this week's פרשה, parsha, ואתחנן. Va'etchanan. The פסוקים pesukim of שמע Shema
is very beautifully timed with this week's פרשה parsha as well, which
it says that you shall say these words בשכבך ובקומך beshochbecha uvekumecha
when you go to sleep and when you rise up. And the
question is, how do you read those words 'go to sleep' and
'rise up'? Does that mean the time when you are going to
bed, or does that mean during the time when you will be
sleeping? So or maybe both. So when you begin to go to
bed is at nightfall. That seems to be agreed in this משנה,
Mishna, especially at a time where there's no electrical light, so people
basically worked from daybreak but they went to bed at night when
the day turned dark. But the question is till how late into
the night. So if it's only the time when people are heading
off to bed, then it's only maybe a few hours, maybe even
less, so only a few hours into the night. If it includes
the entire time of sleeping, then it would be all the way
until daybreak. The question is the middle position that says חצות, chatzos,
which the משנה Mishna now turns itself to. That's a question not
yet. So let's take a look at the rest of the
משנה. Mishna. מעשה ובאו בניו מבית המשתה. Ma'aseh uba'u banav mibeis hamishteh.
There was a story that the children of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
came back from the drinking house. Now, משתה mishteh might also mean
that it was a wedding party, but somehow it was a place
where they were out all night having a good time, probably doing
a good deal of drinking. Maybe they were not in the thinking
house. about or in the right state of mind to be saying
שמע Shema or to be דאוונען davening and they came home and
אמרו לו amru lo they said to him: לא קרינו את שמע,
lo karinu et shema, we have not yet said the שמע. Shema.
אמר להם amar lahem he said to them: אם לא עלה עמוד
השחר חייבים אתם לקרות. im lo ala amud hashachar chayavim atem likrot.
If the morning star has not yet arisen you are still obligated
and you also may still say it and it's fine you can
still say it. So here ruling according to his position.
And then the משנה mishna continues and says the following: ולא זו
בלבד אמרו, velo zo bilvad amru, maybe this is Rabban Gamliel's statement
not clear if it's the משנה mishna taking over or Rabban Gamliel.
Not only regarding this did they say אלא כל מה שאמרו חכמים
עד חצות מצותן עד שיעלה עמוד השחר. ela kol mah she-amru chachamim
ad chatzot mitzvatan ad she-ya'aleh amud hashachar. Anything that the sages say
you really only have till midnight, the real הלכה halakhah is that
the מצוה mitzvah goes all through the night. There is no הלכתי
halakhic time of really of midnight, meaning as a הלכתי halakhically significant.
I mean certainly midnight was when there was מכת בכורות makat bechorot
but in terms of like a significance, here and there sometimes you
find the idea of like midday, but basically הלכה halakhah doesn't recognize
that as a significant time. So when they would, so the sages
would say until midnight, midnight is really not the real time that
limits to you saying שמע, Shema, you can really say שמע Shema
the whole night. So then why are they saying midnight? Because, so
first we're going to give some examples, for example not only this:
הקטר חלבים ואיברים מצותן עד שיעלה עמוד השחר. hektar chalavim ve-eivarim mitzvatan
ad she-ya'aleh amud hashachar. When you would burn the fats and the
limbs of a sacrifice, the limbs for an עולה, olah, the fats
of all sacrifices, you could burn them throughout the night. The sacrifice
would have to be offered in the day, the blood sprinkled in
the day, but the fats and the limbs could be offered the
entire, burnt on the altar the entire night. If they, however, were
left off the altar the entire night then they could not be
burnt by the following day. Similarly, וכל הנאכלים ליום אחד, ve-chol han-ne'echalim
leyom echad, all קרבנות korbanot that are eaten for one day, which
is primarily the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim like the holiest of קרבנות,
korbanot, the חטאת chatat and the אשם asham which are eaten by
the כהנים kohanim for one day, and also what a, the קרבן
korban that a ישראל Yisrael eats, normally it's a שלמים, shelamim, he'll
eat that for two days, but there is one called a תודה,
todah, a קרבן korban of thanksgiving which they actually eat only for
a day and the following night. So all of those that are
eaten for one day מצותן עד שיעלה עמוד השחר, mitzvatan ad she-ya'aleh
amud hashachar, you really can, the מצוה mitzvah is until daybreak. אם
כן למה אמרו חכמים עד חצות? im ken lamah amru chachamim ad
chatzot?
So if the מצוה mitzvah is until daybreak, why did the sages
say until midnight? כדי להרחיק אדם מן העבירה kedei leharchik adam min
ha-aveirah
in order to distance you from the sin. If you think I've
got the whole night to say it, so you keep on pushing
it off and pushing it off and next thing you know you've
fallen asleep or you've gotten drunk and you forgot to say it.
So therefore they told you you have to say it by midnight.
But really you're allowed to say it the entire night. Now two
points about this, or a few points about this. Number one is
רש"י Rashi first of all points out that the burning of the
fats they never said has to be by midnight. That was just
stuck in because it was part of this statement about the eating
of the sacrifices. But really that really could, they never even made
this requirement up until midnight. But at least by the eating of
the sacrifices and by saying of the שמע, Shema, maybe those are
things that people might not prioritize as much. First of all it's
not limited to כהנים, kohanim, you know maybe the כהנים kohanim take
all of their rituals that they're doing in the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash super seriously. Also because you know it's eating, it's not a
ritual per se. So those are areas where people might be at
least by the sacrifices people might be a little bit more lax
and the שמע, Shema, yeah I'll have time, I have time, I
have time, and then you never get around to saying it. So
these are things where they said you have to do it by
חצות. chatzot. Now the question is, first of all, is this part
of what Rabban Gamliel is saying or is this the משנה mishna
sort of you know sort of inserting in. If it's what Rabban
Gamliel is saying, then what Rabban Gamliel is saying is like look,
in principle I agree you're supposed to do it until midnight, but
if you missed it, I'm really telling you you have the whole
night. Okay, and that's one way of reading what he's saying. But
normally it's understood that this is not or whatever, it's part, you
know it could be read as this is not Rabban Gamliel's statement.
Rabban Gamliel's saying I don't even think you're supposed to wait, you
know you have the midnight limit even rabbinically. I think you do
it the whole night. And then the משנה mishna is sort of
you know is sort of saying and by the way even the
rabbis that say midnight, they also agree in principle to Rabban Gamliel
that you actually have the whole night. So there's a little question
whether this last phrase is Rabban Gamliel sort of a little bit
agreeing to the rabbis as what you should, you know you should
be shooting for midnight, or is it sort of a comment on
the rabbis that even the rabbis in principle agree to Rabban Gamliel.
A few other comments before we start the גמרא. gemara. First of
all I want to say something since we are starting now ש"ס
Shas for the next time, some of the for the you know
once again for some of the sort of implications here in terms
of or certainly implications, some of the assumptions or some of what
we see when we first sort of like open the first מסכת
masekhet of the גמרא. gemara. First of all let's take a step
back. Why do we begin with ברכות? Berachot? Well we begin with
זרעים Zeraim because you know זרעים Zeraim is the first tractate, the
first סדר, seder, the first order of משנה mishna and ברכות Berachot
is the beginning of זרעים. Zeraim. Now ברכות Berachot is the beginning
of זרעים Zeraim because you make blessings over the agriculture, maybe you
could say it's the first one, you make blessings before you benefit,
before you eat, although really, as we know, the tractates are ordered
within a order based within a section based on size. So ברכות
Brachos has the most chapters, it's the first they're ordered based on
the size. But it is interesting first of all to note that
ברכות Brachos is is in the agricultural section because it is true
a section of it has to deal with blessings over food but
a lot of it has to do with שמע, Shma, תפילה, Tefila,
blessings over a whole range of things and why how it fits
into agriculture, you know, it might be a hook, might be there's
no better place to put it is not so clear. I would
like to make the following sort of suggestion in terms of what
ברכות Brachos is doing here and in generally the order of the
entire sort of track order of of the משנה, Mishnah, which is
that in one way, yes, זרעים Zraim is about agriculture, but in
another way if you think about it, the order of זרעים Zraim
is really about daily life. Right? Daily life in an agricultural society
is a lot about your planting and your harvesting and your reaping
and sort of the appropriate rituals that are part of that which
are all of the agricultural gifts and so on. Well another central
part of the daily life of course is the prayer, the שמונה
עשרה, Shmone Esrei, the תפילה, Tefila, the ברכות Brachos and so on.
So to think about זרעים Zraim a little bit more broadly because
if you think about it, the aspects of daily life are not
really there's nothing that's devoted to them you know as a tractate.
And that's how I would more broadly like to think of זרעים
Zraim and then if you think about it in order of all
of these sections of ש"ס Shas of the six tractates of the
six orders, you can I think see a progression because you move
from daily life to the special days, to the מועדי, Moadei, שבת,
Shabbos, יום טוב Yom Tov and so on which is the next
order. Then you move that's sort of one way of moving in
terms of daily life and special days of the year. You also
go from the private as it were to a little bit broadening
to this larger sort of sense of family because the next order
is נשים. Nashim. נשים Nashim often translated as women, also might mean
actually wives, the same word in Hebrew, and clearly that is a
shift towards much more discussions about, yes, again from the male perspective
which is why it's focusing on women as what is being introduced,
but that's sort of the move of from the individual to the
family life and so much about that tractate is really about that
order is really about the family life. And then after that, so
you have your daily life, your special days, you as an individual,
you as your family life, then you move out into the broader
society, which is the next order which is נזיקין, Nezikin, which is
about sort of civil law, interpersonal law, damages, not limited to damages,
courts, you know, and so on, it's you sort of interacting with
the larger society. And only at the very end you get קדשים
Kodshim and טהרות Taharos entering into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the
purity demands in order to enter into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and so on. So to one degree it could be seen as
that all of it is leading up to sort of this entering
into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash as the ideal but in a
very different way it could be seen very differently that what basically
defines our lives as religious sanctified lives, you know, is mostly determined
before you even get to קדשים Kodshim and טהרות. Taharos. It's mostly
determined by the שמע Shma and the שמונה עשרה Shmone Esrei and
the ברכות Brachos and how when we go out into the world
and we do our agriculture, the gifts that we give, you know,
from the crops and then special days, the ימים טובים, Yamim Tovim,
how we interact with them during individuals, how we interact in our
families. So that really defines the bulk of what our religious life
is even well well before you get to the very end which
is the קדשים Kodshim and טהרות. Taharos. So I'd like to first
of all just share that as a thought in terms of the
whole structure of ש"ס Shas and why we begin with ברכות. Brachos.
Moving beyond that to the specific issues here, it's worth noting a
couple of things that are implicit in the משנה, Mishnah, which anybody
who's been sort of learning גמרא Gemara maybe is implicitly aware of
but I wanted to just bring it out. Number one is the
idea that it assumes you're already in the conversation. When do we
read שמע Shma at night? Well, you didn't even tell me there's
a מצוה Mitzvah to say שמע, Shma, right? You're just you know
that's all taken for granted. Well, when do we? Okay? And then
the answer is, well, based on some other ritual practice that of
course you're aware of. When the כהנים Kohanim go to eat their
תרומה, Truma, right? Assumes that you know that there's a time that
they go to eat their תרומה, Truma, that there was a problem,
that they had to wait until that time and so on, so
it assumes that you're very much engaged already in the conversation. I
think what's also significant about the next stage is that it actually
also introduces rabbinic law in the first משנה. Mishnah. It says really
you can do it the whole night, but the rabbis said until
חצות Chatzos להרחיק אדם מן העבירה. le'harchik adam min ha'aveira. Because this
really already communicates to you the dual role that's being played here.
On the one, it's the rabbis as interpreting the Torah law. When
do you say שמע? Shma? The rabbis are going to tell you
when you say שמע. Shma. But in the end there's going to
be debate. But at the end of the day, that is a
question about your biblical obligation. There's another entire role that the rabbis
are playing, which is that they're also legislating and they're sometimes sort
of saying, you know, that might be your biblical obligation but we're
going to try to protect you, protect you, you know, from transgression,
we're going to say until midnight. And so much of what sort
of of what licenses or legitimates, you know, or motivates the Rabbis
to be making their rulings, not their interpretive rulings, but their legislative
rulings is because, you know, the idea of ועשו משמרת למשמרתי, va'asu
mishmeret lemishmarti, make a fence around my teaching, protect my teaching, that
their role is, you know, self-understood as protecting people from transgression. So
there's an enormous amount in addition to just שמע Shema that's already
sort of communicated here in this first משנה. Mishnah. The very fact
at the end also that it says, oh, everything the Rabbis said,
like when they talked about burning sacrifices, who the heck is thinking
about burning sacrifices? That's way at the end of all of ש"ס.
Shas. But again, there's this assumption that if you're in this conversation,
then you're total then you're in the conversation and you're sort of
and that is part of why it is both exhilarating but also
perhaps perhaps challenging to jump in because it assumes that you're completely
in the conversation. Okay, Jeff, quick question, then we'll jump into the
גמרא.
Gemara. So at this point are we thinking at all about שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei or are they thinking that שמע Shema just goes
with שמע Shema or they're in a synagogue dealing with it?
You mean why didn't they say we have to daven שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei yet?
Or שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei the time you're supposed to say שמונה
עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. Yeah, that's a different that's a different path, chapter and
even while saying that here it doesn't totally start at the beginning
so you have a מצוה mitzvah to say שמע, Shema, I should
say that ברכות Berakhot is much more what we would consider well-organized
than other מסכתות. masechtot. One chapter dealing with שמע, Shema, then dealing
with שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, then you know dealing with ברכת המזון,
Birkat Hamazon, and it starts by saying when does my obligation begin?
So this actually is very logically ordered, goes in a progression, and
yes, we'll look at שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei down the line but
not not dealing with it. Okay, let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנא היכא קאי דקתני מאימתי? Tanna heicha kai d'katani
me'eimatai?
Where was our תנא Tanna standing, that he at the author of
the משנה Mishnah standing that he said when מאימתי, me'eimatai, from when
do you say שמע Shema at night? Meaning like what was the
context? Well, there is no context, it's at the very beginning. Okay,
but again this somewhat is pointing to the point like first tell
me you have an obligation, what do you mean when do you
start saying? So what is this sort of responding you know in
reference to? The two and in addition
מאי שנא דתני ערבית ברישא, mai shna d'tani arvit be'reisha, why here
do we first talk about your evening obligation? לתני דשחרית ברישא, litni
deshacharit be'reisha, first talk about your morning obligation. Very fascinating because we
know הלכתית halachically days start in the in the
night, so I just this seems like a real softball question, right?
תנא אקרא קאי. Tanna akra kai. Yeah, he was referring to the
פסוק, pasuk, דכתיב בשכבך ובקומך, dechtiv beshachbecha uvkumecha, that you say the
שמע Shema when you go to sleep and when you wake up,
והכי קתני זמן קריאת שמע דשכיבה אימת. vehachi katani zman krias Shema
deshchiva eimat.
So this is the implicit point that's being made. This is sort
of exactly that issue that you're already in the conversation, we all
know there's a מצוה mitzvah to say שמע, Shema, we all know
that the תורה Torah says you do it when you go to
sleep and when you rise up. So זמן קריאת שמע דשכיבה, zman
krias Shema deshchiva, the שמע Shema of the going to sleep, אימת,
eimat, when does that begin? משעה שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול
בתרומתן, mishe'ah shehakohanim nichnasim le'echol bitrumatan, when the כהנים kohanim come in
to eat from their תרומה. trumah. So it's implicitly in reference to
that
verse. ואיבעית אימא, v'ee bayit eima, if you want I could say
יליף מבריאתו של עולם, yalif mivriato shel olam, it's learning out from
the creation of the world, דכתיב ויהי ערב ויהי בוקר יום אחד.
dechtiv vayehi erev vayehi voker yom echad. It's not based on בשכבך
ובקומך, beshachbecha uvkumecha, or at least the reason it speaks about night
first is because you know the whole Jewish day begins at night
and therefore it starts at night first. Okay, so then the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי, ee hachi, fine, but if so סיפא דקתני,
seifa d'katani, at the end when we say this is when we
move into the ברכות berachos of שמע, Shema, not even yet שמונה
עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, but the ברכות berachos of שמע, Shema, בשחר מברך
שתים לפניה ואחת לאחריה, bashachar mevarech shtayim lefaneha ve'achat leachareha,
in the morning you say two ברכות berachos before שמע Shema and
one after, right? You say the ברכה berachah of יוצר המאורות Yotzer
Hame'orot and
אהבה רבה, Ahava Rabba, right? And you end with גאל ישראל. Ga'al
Yisrael. So and ובערב מברך שתים לפניה ושתים לאחריה. uva'erev mevarech shtayim
lefaneha ushtayim leachareha.
Okay, you have two ברכות berachos after the שמע. Shema. So there
it first talks about morning and then night. לתני דערבית ברישא, litni
d'arvit be'reisha, why not be consistent? If you're talking about first שמע
Shema at night, שמע Shema in the morning, then say about the
ברכות berachos of the night שמע, Shema, the ברכות berachos of the
day שמע. Shema. So the גמרא Gemara says תנא פתח בערבית והדר
תנא בשחרית, Tanna patach be'arvit vehadar tanna beshacharit, gives a very straightforward
literary answer. The תנא Tanna opened with the night שמע Shema for
the reasons we said and then he's talked about the morning שמע.
Shema. עד דקאי בשחרית פריש מילי דשחרית, ad d'kai beshacharit peirish mili
deshacharit, now that we're talking about the morning שמע, Shema, פריש מילי
דשחרית, peirish mili deshacharit, so he ends he continues to discuss aspects
of the morning שמע, Shema, the ברכות berachos before and after, והדר
פריש מילי דערבית, vahadar peirish mili de'arvit, and then he goes back
and discusses the ברכות berachos of the night of the night שמע.
Shema. This is called I believe a A-B-B-A chiastic structure. Right, so
that's a so therefore yeah the literary structure, yeah, but you're going
to start at night. Very straightforward. I would like to point out
though that by just you know sort of casually mentioning the verse
of when you go to sleep and when you wake up and
also mentioning the idea of ויהי ערב ויהי בוקר, vayehi erev vayehi
voker, what we really it seems to be
Is the time of
the and the day שמע? Shema? Is basically an understanding of nighttime
and daytime, and then we would look towards classic הלכתי halakhic definitions
of nighttime and daytime, or is it no, this is a unique
time period of obligation based on going to sleep and waking up
and not specifically a definition of nighttime and daytime. So that, for
example, the position that says that you can do it the entire
night, maybe it's not because you sleep the entire night, maybe it's
because that position understands there's a night שמע Shema and a day
שמע. Shema. So if there's a night שמע, Shema, you do it
the entire night. So by quoting those two verses, it really is
suggesting two different models of how we understand the times of שמע
Shema and what they are based on. Charlie, you want to jump
in?
So the משנה Mishnah does have a thing about the burning of
the
fats, but in קרבנות, Korbanot, it does, they
start with morning, which
kind of doesn't fit here.
Right, so that's a good point too, and that's a little bit
why תוספות Tosafot says we even ask the question. But again, why,
and maybe because maybe you could argue a little bit because prayer
is to some degree based on קרבנות Korbanot or maybe that was
explaining what the question was based on. But some questions are really
not questions. I think they're just layups for the answer, which one
gets the feeling here. And I do think it nicely frames sort
of the implicit context and also two possible models for what the
idea of שמע Shema is. Yes.
Yeah, I mean, because, you know, it would have been, it's pretty
interesting, like what you said, that if you don't like the verse
that's talking essentially about the מצוה mitzvah we're talking at hand, we'll
give you another verse that's, you know, less contextual. Right, so it's
in addition, it's
just, and I just think as we will see that that is
somehow does inform exactly the ongoing conversation.
So let's, yeah, and
okay, let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר מר, Amar Mar, משעה שהכהנים נכנסים
לאכול בתרומתן. mishe'ah shehakohanim nichnasim le'echol bitrumatan. So now to the next
line. When does it start? When the כהנים kohanim begin to enter
in to eat their תרומה. trumah. מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look.
כהנים אימת קא אכלי בתרומה? Kohanim eimat ka achli bitrumah? When do
כהנים kohanim begin eating their תרומה? trumah? If you're טמא tamei in
the day, you're impure, you touch something that, a dead body, a
carcass of an animal, so you go to the מקוה mikvah that
day and you become complete, you're partially טהור, tahor, you have some
residual טומאה, tumah, and you become completely טהור tahor at nightfall. ובא
השמש וטהר, Uva hashemesh vetaher, says
the תורה. Torah. The sun sets and you become pure. So this
is now at that point the כהנים kohanim can now eat תרומה.
trumah. So כהנים אימת קא אכלי בתרומה, kohanim eimat ka achli bitrumah,
when do they eat תרומה? trumah? משעת צאת הכוכבים. mishe'at tzeit hakochavim.
That's when the stars come out, which is as we know הלכתית
halakhically nightfall. So ליתני משעת צאת הכוכבים, lisni mishe'at tzeit hakochavim, say
when the stars come out. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says, no.
מילתא אגב אורחא קא משמע לן. Milta agav orcha ka mashma lan.
This is sort of telling you something in passing. What is it
telling you in passing? כהנים אימת קא אכלי בתרומה. Kohanim eimat ka
achli bitrumah. In passing, it's telling you, by the way, you know
when כהנים kohanim eat תרומה? trumah? משעת צאת הכוכבים mishe'at tzeit hakochavim
from the time that the stars come out. Now there is a
little problem with that. Why does it say you say שמע Shema
when the כהנים kohanim eat תרומה? trumah? Why not say when the
stars come out? No, because it tells you when the כהנים kohanim
eat תרומה, trumah, so that way it tells you, informs you that
you say it when the stars come out. That's the problem with
that answer. How do you know they eat תרומה trumah when the
stars come out? And it's not clear in other משניות, mishnayot, other
משניות mishnayot say like, you know, when it's הערב שמשו. ha'erev shimsho.
It doesn't say when the stars come out. Where so what do
you mean we find that out in passing? So we're going to
see when we turn the page that there's a תוספתא Tosefta which
the גמרא Gemara will quote, which is like a parallel work to
the משנה, Mishnah, that ends the statement that way. It says משעה
שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול בתרומתן mishe'ah shehakohanim nichnasim le'echol bitrumatan from צאת tzeit
and then it says משעת צאת הכוכבים. mishe'at tzeit hakochavim.
Okay, so it explicitly says that that's צאת הכוכבים. tzeit hakochavim. So
again, somehow you somehow know that because maybe you've read also the
תוספתא Tosefta parallel to this. So by talking about that, it is
also telling you that that is, you know, it's telling you two
things if you read the תוספתא. Tosefta. It's telling you that שמע
Shema is צאת הכוכבים tzeit hakochavim and the כהנים kohanim eat the
תרומה trumah at צאת הכוכבים. tzeit hakochavim.
Unless they assume you know that the אשמורת הראשונה ashmoret harishonah starts
with צאת. tzeit. Interesting.
So then the, so and then the, so until then, I see.
So עד סוף האשמורת ad sof ha'ashmoret implied that you're beginning at
the beginning of the אשמורת. ashmoret.
The תוספתא Tosefta is beginning explicit, but the משנה Mishnah assumed you
knew it like it.
It could be, it could be, but it also assumes that that
if we're going to say until the end of the אשמורת, ashmoret,
we're also suggesting that it begins at the beginning of the אשמורת,
ashmoret, which is also not necessarily right. But there certainly is some
other assumptions that you are making or other texts that you're aware
of that let you know that it's צאת הכוכבים. tzeit hakochavim. Now
before we continue, I should mention by the way, again the two
models we put out there, that saying צאת הכוכבים, tzeit hakochavim, even
if it's the same time as when the כהנים kohanim eat their
תרומה, trumah, is really suggesting two very different models. If I tell
you שמע Shema starts at צאת, tzeit, so you think, okay, it's
based on
הלכתית halakhically nightfall and daybreak. It's about night and day. If I
say שמע Shema starts when the כהנים kohanim come back to the
city and whatever, come back home and now eat their תרומה, trumah,
oh, so it's when everybody's coming home and getting ready for night
and going to sleep and so on. It suggests the very different
model of going to sleep and waking up, not the idea of
night and day. and day. So that also I think is a
very sort of different type of a model. I also did want
to say something that we'll continue to see, but I just wanted
to mention this and goes back to my opening theme about daily
life is that I think in מסכת ברכות, Masechet Berachot, you get
much more of a slice of life than you do in any
other מסכת. masechet. You find out about כהנים Kohanim coming home to
eat their תרומה. terumah. We're going to turn the page and you're
going to find out about when do poor people start eating? When
do you start eating on ערב שבת? Erev Shabbat? What happens if
you're up in a tree and it's time to say שמע? Shema?
What happens if you're going on a journey and it's time to
say שמע? Shema? We find out in the משנה Mishnah of רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel's sons were out carousing and they came home late
at night. So it's a very fascinating slice of life and I
think that it fits in very much to the verses of שמע
Shema which are בשבתך בביתך ובלכתך בדרך ובשכבך ובקומך, beshivtecha beveitecha uvelechtecha
vaderech uveshochbecha uviekumecha, that
this is something that you do that sort of is in all
parts of your daily life when you're sitting and when you're walking,
when you're lying and when you're getting up. So that whole sense
of the real daily life is very pronounced here and very also
I think tied in to the time of saying שמע, Shema, which
is a very different model from the night and day model. Yes.
Were כהנים Kohanim actually eating תרומה terumah when this was
written?
That is an excellent point. Certainly not when the
well, I shouldn't say certainly not. Look, there was תרומה terumah after
the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. There's a discussion if
it was דאורייתא d'Oraita or דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. So in principle the we
want to forget about that.
Well, that's also true and that's like another larger discussion as well
which is sort of also ties into ברכות Berachot as opposed to
קדשים, Kodashim, which is how much is there an attempt to try
to transfer
the קדושה kedushah of a world of
מקדש Mikdash into a post-מקדש Mikdash world.
So there's really no reason to bring that.
So that is another excellent point. I don't think that is a
really good point and I appreciate that, that yes, it is also
sort of alluding to those other aspects of קדושה kedushah that may
not be as much part of our lives and that maybe also
to some degree bringing them into in certain ways into what is
now our daily life. Yes, thank you.
Yeah, I had a question about the נכנסים. nichnasim. Where are they
entering?
So I suggested yeah,
I'll just add to that. The אשמורה הראשונה ashmurah harishonah
everybody can figure out when it is. Right. But people may not
be כהנים. Kohanim. They may be so distant that it's a very
artificial.
Right. So I think that the answer to the second point is
exactly Rachel's point that we do want to sort of introduce that
awareness and that phenomenon into the mindset. And as far as the
first point about נכנסים, nichnasim, so what I suggested was that the
מקואות mikvaot were a little bit
now, again, trying to remember because certainly the houses of the כהנים
Kohanim near the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, they found מקואות mikvaot in
the home. Right. But what about southern more?
No,
the גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbat makes it sound that they went
to the that the כהנים Kohanim went to the מקוה mikvah right
before
nightfall. So I don't know why.
Not everybody would see that.
What? Right. But I'm saying I think that the נכנסים nichnasim is
that somehow the מקואות mikvaot are a little bit distant and they're
coming back from the מקוה. mikvah. So they're נכנסים nichnasim to their
homes?
Yes,
that's the way I understood it. Okay. All right. So let's now
continue.
Yes, please. משעה שהכהנים
נכנסים. misha'ah shehaKohanim nichnasim.
That's going to be another version of that will be. But again,
I think that that is exactly what puts us into
the slice of life. You're not just talking about an abstract law,
you're allowed to eat תרומה terumah now. You all of a sudden
picture כהנים Kohanim walking out of the מקוה, mikvah, coming back
home. You're there. You're in that life. And that is so on
the one hand, it's Rachel's point of connected to that world of
קדושה kedushah and I would also say my point about connected to
the real daily life of people and how this is that is
the whole idea of the שמע. Shema. Yes.
Could the introduction of the כהנים Kohanim and also the bringing of
the fats be a way of introducing the idea of תפילה tefillah
or שמע Shema as עבודה שבלב? avodah shebalev?
Well, שמע Shema is not really categorized as עבודה שבלב. avodah shebalev.
שמע Shema has a whole sense about כוונה kavanah which we'll get
to and how do you want to see the connection?
Because they're bringing in
כהנים Kohanim and עבודה avodah and the fats and so on that
you have both the כהנים Kohanim and the עבודה. avodah. Yeah, I
think that that's a very very good point and again, it connects
to Rachel's point that the whole משנה Mishnah is also in many
ways the כהנים Kohanim and the עבודה avodah bringing in that whole
other world and talking about sort of in a way sort of
transferring that world to a post-מקדש Mikdash world. So that's yes, beautifully
said. Okay. So now we continue. So it says like this. So
yeah, you'll somehow know that it's צאת הכוכבים tzet hakochavim and that
that and that tells you and once you know that you know
two things. והא קמשמע לן, veha kamashma lan, it's also teaching us
דכפרה לא מעכבא, dekapparah lo me'akva, that atonement does not prevent you
from eating תרומה. terumah. What does this mean? I will first read
this גמרא Gemara like רש״י Rashi and then tell you how תוספות
Tosafot reads it. כדתניא, K'de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Braisa. ובא
השמש וטהר, U-va hashemesh v'taher,
this is a verse in the תורה Torah which says if a
person becomes טמא Tamei by touching something, then they are טמא Tamei
for that day, they go to the מקווה Mikvah that day, and
night falls and they become טהור, tahor, they become pure. ביאת שמשו
מעכבתו מלאכול בתרומה, Bi'at shimsho me'akvato mi'le'echol bi'terumah, the coming of the
sun, the setting of the sun, holds him back from eating תרומה,
terumah, because once a person goes to the מקווה, mikvah, their only
תרומה terumah is residual and if they normally touch things in that
are not sanctified it has no effect, it only has an effect
of touching תרומה terumah and sacrifices until, until actually sunset, then even
the residual תרומה terumah goes off. So the coming of the sun
holds him back from eating תרומה, terumah, ואין כפרתו מעכבתו מלאכול בתרומה,
ve'ein kaparato me'akvato mi'le'echol bi'terumah, but his the כפרה, kaparah, which רש"י
Rashi says means if you have to bring a sacrifice, that doesn't
hold you back. Now that is not what the verse is talking
about. The verse is talking about people with a one-day טומאה, tumah,
but there's some people that have a seven-day טומאה, tumah, like a
person that has צרעת, tzara'at, right, what we would call leprosy loosely,
or a זב zav for example, and those types of people, a
man with an unusual flow and so on, those types of people
or a woman with an unusual flow and so on, those types
of people, זבה, zavah, do not become fully pure until they bring
a sacrifice, they wait seven days, go to the מקווה, mikvah, and
then bring a sacrifice the next day. And in that period after
nightfall before the sacrifice, they can handle תרומה, terumah, but they can't
handle sacrifices. So you get it, once they go to the מקווה,
mikvah, they can handle any non-sanctified until nightfall of the end of
the period, one day or seven days, then after nightfall they handle
תרומה, terumah, and if they need a sacrifice the next day for
one of these seven-dayers, then you handle sacrifices after you've brought the
sacrifice. So the גמרא Gemara says, maybe this is telling me you
don't have to wait for the sacrifice to handle תרומה. terumah. Now
again, the funny thing is that the verses are talking about one
day, not seven-dayers, but we'll bracket that point. Okay, so that's what
I learn out. ואין כפרתו, Ve'ein kaparato, because it says we'll get
there. ובא השמש, U-va hashemesh, so sunset, the setting of the sun
is what's significant, not the bringing of sacrifices. וממאי דהאי ובא השמש,
U-mmai de-hai u-va ha-shemesh, how do you know the setting of the
sun? ביאת שמשו Bi'at shimsho means the setting of the sun? והאי
וטהר טהר יומא, Ve-hai v'taher taher yoma, and then he becomes pure
means, now it didn't say that he becomes pure, it says that
the day becomes pure, which means that the day is fully over,
the day, it's sort of the day is cleansed, we're done with
the day, so the sun set because remember, we don't just have
to get till sunset, we have to get till צאת, Tzeit, till
the stars come out, so the sun set and then the light
totally is removed, the day is cleansed as it were, there's no
light left, it is totally dark, stars come out. That's how we
know the idea of the stars. What tells you to read it
that way, that that's when you become totally pure? דילמא ביאת אורו
הוא, Dilma bi'at oro hu, maybe it means not that the sun
set, again I'll read this רש"י's Rashi's ways, but maybe it means
the sun rises, בא, ba, where is it coming, you know, going,
so maybe it means it rises. ומאי וטהר, U-mai v'taher, and what
does it mean he becomes pure? Not that the day is fully
over, but טהר גברא, teher gavra, that he purifies himself by bringing
his sacrifices and maybe you have to wait for him to bring
his sacrifices. That's again this is
רש"י's Rashi's speak. No, אמר רבה בר רב שילא, Amar Rabbah bar
Rav Shila, אי הכי לימא קרא Ei hachi leima kra ויתהר, ve'yitehar,
he shall bring his sacrifices. מאי וטהר, Mai v'taher, which is more
sort of like automatically it becomes pure, so if he had to
do something it wouldn't say that. So it means טהר יומא, teher
yoma, the day becomes completely cleansed and you're fully done with the
day and it's fully nightfall and that's enough. כדאמרי אינשי, K'de'amri inshi,
like people say, איערב שמשא ואידכי יומא, I'arev shimsha ve'idchi yoma, the
sun has set and the day has been cleansed, the day is
completely over. So that's what we learn that what we're also learning
is that it's not just sunset, it's actually the stars coming out.
Now תוספות Tosafot gets into a, you know, a real conniption I
would say because he says, first of all, he doesn't say this
point but I will say it, the verse isn't talking about a
sacrifice, about seven-day טומאה, tumah, it's talking about one-day טומאה. tumah. Number
two תוספות Tosafot says, there's, you know, we know from plenty of
places that you can eat תרומה terumah from, you know, once the
stars come out, that you don't need to wait to bring sacrifices
to eat תרומה. terumah. So תוספות Tosafot says the question is, which
is more really fits the context more, how do you know it's
when the stars come out? Maybe it's when the sun sets. The
תורה Torah says the sun will set and you'll be pure, so
maybe it just means sunset, what tells you you have to wait
till the stars come out? So it says no, here's how we
read it: the sun sets, ובא השמש, u-va ha-shemesh, וטהר, v'taher, the
day is cleansed, it's not enough that the sun sets, all the
light has to be removed from the day and then you're okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says how do you know that, how to
read it? Maybe it means ובא השמש, u-va ha-shemesh, the sun sets,
וטהר, v'taher, and you be and you become pure, which is certainly
the simple read of the verse, as soon as the sun set
you become pure, not that the day is cleansed and you need
it for the stars to come out. And as it says okay,
so then it would have more emphasized the he, that the he
becomes pure, ויתהר, ve'yitehar, and the answer then, the question is so
good, the answer is not as satisfying, but anyway that's exactly how
תוספות Tosafot reads the question. How do you know it means two
stages, sun setting and stars coming out, maybe it just means sun
setting? Let's see the גמרא Gemara now repeats this. במערבא Be-ma'arava הדר
רבה בר רב שילא. hadar Rabbah bar Rav Shila. לא שמיע להו.
lo sh'mi'a lehu. And in the West, in Israel, they did not
hear of this point of רבה בר שילא, Rabba bar Shila, a
difference of וטהר v'taher and ויטהר. v'yitaher. That that somehow tells you
the difference. ובעו למיבעי, U'ba'u l'miba'ei, and they ask this question: האי
ובא השמש ביאת שמשו הוא? Hai u'ba hashemesh bi'at shimsho hu? Does
the setting, ובא השמש u'ba hashemesh mean the setting of the sun?
ומאי וטהר טהר יומא? U'mai v'taher, taher yoma? And וטהר v'taher means
the day is cleansed and you have to wait till the stars
to come out? או דילמא, O dilma, and now תוספות's Tosafot way
which fits so much better, או דילמא ביאת אורו הוא? o dilma
bi'at oro hu? Or maybe it means no, as soon as the,
you know, the light has gone away, meaning as soon as the
sun has set? ומאי וטהר טהר גברא? U'mai v'taher, taher gavra? And
then the person automatically becomes pure and then it doesn't need the
stars to come out, just
sunset. והדר פשטוה מברייתא. V'hadar pashitu'ei mibraita. And then interestingly, they didn't
read it from a derivation of the verse of וטהר, v'taher, ויטהר.
v'yitaher. They got it from a ברייתא, braita, from another rabbinic source.
What did this rabbinic source say? This is what I referred to
before. דתניא בברייתא, D'tanya b'braita, because the ברייתא braita teaches: סימן לדבר
צאת הכוכבים. Siman ladavar tzeit hakochavim. What
do you know, when is it that the כהנים Kohanim can eat
their תרומה terumah and they come into their תרומה? terumah? סימן לדבר,
Siman ladavar, when the stars come out. שמע מינה ביאת שמשו הוא.
Shma mina bi'at shimsho hu. You see that the rabbi tell us
that that's what the verse means. You see that in rabbinic tradition
the verse means that the day is not only sunset, but that
the day is completely over, the stars have come out. ומאי וטהר?
U'mai v'taher? And what does וטהר v'taher mean? טהר יומא, taher yoma,
the day has completely, has completely been cleansed. So I want to
actually point out because I've already pointed out in the משנה, Mishnah,
you know, some implicit things that are being communicated about the rabbinic
enterprise. So one is sort of rabbis as interpreters and rabbis as
legislators. Here what you're also getting is, which we mentioned at the
very last day yesterday, the very last day of נדה, Niddah, two
modes of the rabbinic tradition. How do we know what the תורה
Torah means? Do we know it because, well, that's our tradition, we
have that passed down, that's our tradition. How do I know that's
what the verse, well, the rabbi told me, so the rabbi told
me, that's how I know what it means. Or do we say
no, at the end of the day it comes through an engagement
with the verses and, you know, and maybe what we actually have
strayed from tradition is a very minor part of the, of the
tradition, of the law, and the vast majority of it might be
through the creative interaction of the rabbis with the תורה, Torah, with
the verses and deriving it from the verses. And here you exactly
have this. It's a very funny question. How do I know the
verse means this? Answer: How do I know the verse means this,
maybe it means that? So one answer is, oh, because of the
way exactly framed this word. So at least it's on point, you
might not accept the answer, at least it's on point. But the
other answer is how do I know this is what the verse
means and the answer is because the rabbi say so. Okay, it's
a very different type of an answer but it really reflects the
two different modes of the sort of of the whole sense of
rabbinic tradition and מסורה mesorah and the rabbis' understanding of the תורה's
Torah verses.
Yes, here in a way it's possible to say that what the
גמרא Gemara has done is it has transformed one modality into the
other. It opens with we know the verse means this because the
rabbis have said so and the גמרא Gemara has recontextualized
it forcing us to prefer the hermeneutic.
Oh, that's a nice point. That's a very nice point. So you're
saying the ברייתא, braita, which is more of the משנה's Mishnah mode
anyway, which is just sort of apodictic, here's the law. So the
ברייתא braita says, yeah, this is what I'm telling you it means.
And the גמרא, Gemara, which is all about the conversation and the
interaction says, don't just tell me, how do I know? Very beautifully
said, thank you.
The implication in this is the stars come out implies you have
to see stars.
Or for
stars to come out meaning if it's cloudy we don't know the
stars came out. Right. So then there's a question, what if it's
December, January in in Israel and it's pouring and there are clouds
and you can't see the stars? There has to be some decisive
way that they make a decision.
Right. So that is true and nowadays we we deal with the
opposite disability which is we so much say, oh, stars come out,
that's 45 minutes, that's 42 minutes, that's 72 minutes, and we're all
looking at our watches, you know, and and nobody's looking at the
stars and it's completely detached from the real world. So the point
that some people, right, who דאוון ותיקין, daven vatikin, exactly say שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei exactly at the moment of sunrise, right, they get
their exact astronomical 6:23 and 47 seconds, right, and 47 parts of
a second or whatever it is, 47 anyway, whatever. And then that's
fine if you're like in a place with no windows. But they
could be outside or in a place with windows and they're saying
what time did sunrise? So I think we sometimes have the opposite
issue. Yes, if you're dealing in that way there are ways if
you can't look at the stars to estimate the same type of
a time and, you know, some of that does get discussed a
little bit elsewhere, but estimating based on, you know, passage of time.
But at least there was much more connected, as you point out,
to the real world.
I'm still stuck on this for כהנים Kohanim thing because תרומה terumah
is something for Israel.
Yes, the משנה Mishnah was written in Israel.
I understand, but but you're picking something that that really doesn't allow
you to broaden
it.
Alright. So let's keep on, let's go a little bit further. So
I don't know because it's already
8:15, 8:12. Is anybody going to the second מנין? minyan? You are?
Alright. Maybe we'll go just a little bit further. It is our
first day. We have yet to, I see we have yet to
reorient myself into trying to do all of this in... anyway, we
started late so. Yeah, so חברותא? chavruta? The new time is only
starting on Monday?
Okay, I don't know. We're going to go a little further. We're
going to finish this or mostly. Let's take a look. אמר מר,
amar mar, משעה שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול בתרומתן, mishe-asha she-ha-Kohanim nichnasim le-echol be-terumatan,
from
the time that the כהנים Kohanim enter in to eat their תרומה.
Terumah. רמינהו? raminihu? Well, I'll ask you on this: מאימתי קוראים שמע
בערבית? me-ematai korin Shema be-arvit? When do you read שמע Shema at
night? משעני נכנס לאכול פיתו במלח. mishe-ani nichnas le-echol pito be-melach.
There you go. Very different model, right? And not with this world
of קדושה kedusha and so on, but very much slice of life
when the poor person comes in at nightfall to have his, and
not it just says when he starts his meal. Notice again the
detail. What's he eating? He's eating bread with salt. Right, you really
are sort of like in the house there with the poor person.
When he starts, he comes in to eat his bread with salt
עד שעה שעומד לפטור מסעודתו, ad sha-ah she-omed lifator mi-seudato,
until the time when normally his meal is over. So this gives
you a very short period of time to say שמע. Shema. It
really is, and not only when you're going to sleep, I mean,
that's when you're having your meal before going to sleep, but you
say שמע Shema at the time right before you go to sleep.
תוספות Tosafot says, well when is he saying שמע? Shema? He's eating
his meal. So תוספות Tosafot says, makes him right before he starts
the meal. He goes into the house to eat the meal, he
hasn't sat down yet, that's when he says שמע. Shema. But anyway,
very short period of time and it focuses on the poor person.
Okay? So it
says עד... ad... שעה נכנס, sha-ah nichnas, it's better, so maybe...
Right. Because he's out working. Right.
Maybe. Maybe.
That's a good point. That's a good point. So the גמרא Gemara
says סיפא ודאי פליגא אמתניתין, seifa vadai peliga a-matnitin, in the end
it certainly argues on our משנה Mishnah that gives you to the
end of the first watch, midnight or whatever. רישא מי לימא פליגא
אמתניתין? reisha mi leima peliga a-matnitin? And how about the first part?
Does that argue on our משנה? Mishnah? Is when the עני ani
goes in to eat his bread the same time as the כהנים
Kohanim or different time? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no,
it doesn't have to argue. עני וכהן חד שיעורא הוא, ani ve-Kohen
chad shi-ura hu, they could both be the same time. But again,
it's giving you two very different models or, you know, sort of
constellations of ideas, you know, when talking about when the שמע Shema
begins. But they could technically be the same time. So it says
ורמינהו, u-reminhu, okay let me ask you on this: מאימתי מתחילים לקרות
קריאת שמע בערבית? me-ematai matchilin likrot kariat Shema be-arvit? When do you
begin שמע Shema at night? This is the תוספתא, Tosefta, this is
the full thing we alluded to before. משעה שבני אדם נכנסים לאכול
פיתן בערבי שבתות, mishe-asha she-benei adam nichnasim le-echol pattan be-arvei shabbatot,
not the poor person on a normal day, but normal people, middle-class
people when they come in on ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. Okay, when
they come in ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, you got to get in
earlier, a little bit earlier, right? Because you don't work up to
the very last minute and so on. So whatever that time is,
it's when normal people come into their house on ערב שבת. erev
Shabbat. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. וחכמים אומרים, ve-Chachamim omrim,
רש"י Rashi also says that you can start your meal sooner because
you're not going to be preparing into the evening. וחכמים אומרים, ve-Chachamim
omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say, משעה שהכהנים זכאים לאכול בתרומתן. mishe-asha
she-ha-Kohanim zakka-in le-echol be-terumatan.
Right, notice again the different language here, taking us into a more
legal sense and not a slice of life: when the כהנים Kohanim
are allowed to eat their תרומה. Terumah. So we're not seeing the
כהנים Kohanim eating their תרומה, Terumah, but when the law is that
they're allowed to eat their תרומה. Terumah. סימן לדבר צאת הכוכבים, siman
la-davar tzeit ha-kochavim, that is the coming out of the stars. ואף
על פי שאין ראיה לדבר, ve-af al pi she-ein ra-aya la-davar, although
there's no proof that צאת tzeit is when night begins, זכר לדבר,
zecher la-davar, there's a hint. Okay, now this phrase means, by the
way, זכר, zecher, a remembrance, an allusion, a hint. It's not such
an allusion, it's pretty clear, but again it's when you can't learn
something from the תורה Torah and you have to learn it from
the other books from נ"ך NaCH and not תורה, Torah, that it's
not called an, you know, a definitive proof, it's just an allusion.
Actual law can only be learned from תורה. Torah. Okay, sometimes we
don't and then we find a way to say that's okay. But
in principle we only learn straight from the תורה. Torah. Okay, שנאמר,
she-ne'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says: ואנחנו עושים במלאכה, ve-anachnu osim ba-melacha,
we were doing the work, this is when they came back to
build
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. וחציים מחזיקים ברמחים מעלות השחר עד צאת
הכוכבים, ve-chetzyam machzikim ba-remachim me-alot ha-shachar ad tzeit ha-kochavim, half
were holding the spears
from the daybreak until the stars came out. Okay, so how does
that tell you that that is the definition of night and day?
והוא אומר, ve-hu omer, and in another פסוק pasuk says: והיו לנו
הלילה משמר והיום מלאכה. ve-hayu lanu ha-layla mishmar ve-ha-yom melacha.
At night we would watch and it's day we would work. You
see they're doing the work in the day and it says that
it's from the morning star until the stars come out. Now, that's
all very nice, that tells me that that's the definition of night,
that doesn't tell me that that's when the כהנים kohanim eat, that
doesn't tell me that that's when you say שמע. Shema. So again,
maybe it tells me when the כהנים kohanim eat because the תורה
Torah talks about the sun setting. But again, using that and this
is one idea, fully setting is when the stars come out. But
using that as the model for saying שמע Shema again puts us
into more this definition of night and day as opposed to the
going to sleep and waking up, which is the alternative model. Okay,
you wanted to say something, David?
No, so to build upon your point of saying that there's a
difference between night and day and human action. Right? Sounds like they're
actually, there's maybe, perhaps there are three categories. Yeah. One, and the
human action is broken up into categories of regulated time, like the
כהנים, kohanim, the זמן zman for the כהנים kohanim to eat, and
there is actually sociological time, when the עניים aniyim come and go,
I think they can come and go whenever they want to do
it.
Right. That's a good point. So what you're saying is the reason
the כהנים kohanim could be framed in both ways, they come in
when they're permitted because that reflects a certain, what do you call,
regulated time. So it allows it to be, in my two models,
it allows it to be categorized either way. Yes.
Can we see a muted social criticism here? You have the כהנים
kohanim who are living off other people, you know, gifts and tithes,
and then you have the עניים aniyim who are, you know, it's
telling us they're just eating bread and salt. And then you have
the regular people. So which is the standard? Right.
I don't know. It's hard to read a criticism, it certainly is
highly descriptive. It's descriptive, but what's the commentary?
An observation.
You are inserting the commentary! It's providing the description!
But they have to decide which class of people are we...
oh I see, the question of, oh you're saying... oh, I see,
I see, I see. Oh, okay, I got it, I got it,
I got it.
I see. So that's an excellent point. You're saying which, not the
fact that you have these three descriptions, but which model you want
to look at sort of talks to, are we thinking about the
elite? Are we thinking about sort of the middle class? Are we
thinking about, you know, even the poor? Who do we think about
in terms of when... and who's the audience, in the sense who's
the model, who's the audience. That's a very beautiful point. Thank you.
Okay, so now let's continue. The גמרא Gemara says, so it says
like this. Okay. מאי ואומר, mai ve'omer, why do you need another
verse? You know, if we just said, look, from daybreak until the
stars come out. וכי תימא, vechi teima, דכי מיחשך ליה עדיפא, dechi
meichashach lei adifa,
because you could have said that really, as soon as the sun
sets, that's night, before the stars come out. ואינהו, ve'inhu, they in
the time of the building of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, דמחשיכי
ומקדמי, demachshichi umkadmi, they would go extra late, they go past nightfall
until the stars came out, and they start before
the
day from, you know, the morning star. So maybe their work was
not limited to day, maybe it started earlier and ended later. So
תא שמע, ta shema, no, that's why the other verse tells you,
והיו לנו הלילה משמר, vehayu lanu halaila mishmar, and night we would
watch, והיום מלאכה, vehayom melacha, today we would work. So therefore, this
period of עלות השחר alot hashachar is the definition of day, the
other is the definition of night, and therefore that somehow we then
apply that back to other definitions of night and day, both the
כהנים kohanim but also interestingly the שמע Shema as well.
They were doing these רמחים ramachim from עלות השחר alot hashachar until
צאת הכוכבים, tzet hakochavim, which is day.
I guess even in the day you needed some people to be
guards, but at night everyone, that's all you were doing. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, קסלקא דעתך, kasalka daitach, we're
now going to still work through this issue about are these the
same times but different descriptions, or are they different times? We're assuming,
says the גמרא, Gemara, it's very nice when the גמרא Gemara tells
you what its assumptions are, right? Very often people talk and you
get into arguments and only later you realize it's because you weren't
getting what their assumptions were to begin with. So it helps if
you spell out your assumptions. So the גמרא Gemara sometimes is nice
and it does that for us. So it says קסלקא דעתך, kasalka
daitach, we're assuming דעני ובני אדם חד שיעורא הוא, de'ani uvenei adam
chad shiura hu, that when it says the poor person eats his
bread and it says when people go in on ערב שבת, Erev
Shabbat, then those are the same time. So the גמרא Gemara says
now that we're assuming those are the same time, and a minute
ago we were assuming that the poor person and the כהן kohen
was the same time, now we've got three things that are exactly
the same time with three different descriptions. Now, that itself wouldn't bother
us except that there seems to be a debate, and there can't
be a debate if they're all talking about the same time. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואי אמרת, ve'i amart, if you say עני
וכהן חד שיעורא הוא, ani vechohen chad shiura hu, that the עני
ani and the כהן kohen are also the same time, so חכמים
היינו רבי מאיר. chachamim hayinu Rabbi Meir. So the חכמים chachamim say
that it is when the people go in on ערב שבת, Erev
Shabbat, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, I'm deaf, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the
חכמים chachamim say it's the כהנים. kohanim. So if the כהנים kohanim
is the same as the עני, ani, if they're all the same
then they're not debating. Okay? So they can't all be the same,
some of them have to be different. אלא שמע מינה, ella shema
mina, from here you can see עני שיעורא לחוד וכהן שיעורא לחוד,
ani shiura lachud vechohen shiura lachud, that the time of the עני
ani is different from the time of the כהן. kohen. And but
עני ani and the normal person, the middle class person, that might
be the same. The גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, all you have
to do You don't have to make them all different. You just
have to make two of them different. The גמרא Gemara says, no,
why should we assume the עני ani and the middle-class person are
the same and the כהן kohen is different? Let's say it the
other way. עני וכהן חד שיעורא הוא, ani vekohen chad shiura hu,
like we've been assuming, the עני ani and the כהן kohen are
the same time. ועני ובני אדם לא חד שיעורא הוא, veani uvnei
adam lo chad shiura hu, but the poor person and the normal
person—the middle-class person, I'll say, I'm reflecting גמרא Gemara language—the middle-class person
when it comes on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, that's the different time.
So all three can't be the same time because there's debate. So
you have to say some are different. So let's say the גמרא
Gemara wants to try to argue the עני ani and the כהן
kohen are the same, so fine, let them be the same but
then the בני אדם bnei adam on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, that's
different. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. ואי אמרת עני וכהן חד שיעורא, veee amart
ani vekohen chad shiura, you're still going to try to claim that
the עני ani and the כהן kohen are the same time? רמינהו,
reminu, I'll ask from this. מאימתי מתחילין לקרות שמע בערבין, meimatai matchilin
likro shema baarvin, משעה שקידש היום בערבי שבת, mishashe kidesh hayom baarvei
shabbos, דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer.
Here's a different ברייתא. Braita. When do you begin saying שמע Shema
at night? When the day becomes sanctified on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos.
So here again, purely halakhic time, not what people are doing, purely
halakhic category, when שבת Shabbos begins, which is nightfall. Okay, also interestingly
introducing us into another world of קדושה, kedusha, going back to the
other discussion of the כהנים kohanim world of קדושה. kedusha. Here's a
קדושה kedusha that's part of our world, the world of שבת. Shabbos.
That it could have said, say to the כהנים—sorry, kohanim from the
time the sunset, but it says no, when you begin שבת, Shabbos,
when שבת Shabbos starts. Okay, so that's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which
is effectively sunset. רבי יהושע אומר משעה שהכהנים מטוהרים לאכול בתרומתן. Rabbi
Yehoshua omer mishashe hakohanim mituharin lechol betrumatan.
Similar to when they are entitled to eat their תרומה, truma, but
he's saying when they are fully purified to eat their תרומה. truma.
So, same point but slightly different way of articulating it. Again, notice
here again we're in purely halakhic time now. רבי מאיר אומר משעה
שהכהנים טובלים לאכול בתרומתן. Rabbi Meir omer mishashe hakohanim tovlin lechol betrumatan.
It's when the כהנים kohanim go to the מקוה. mikvah. So now
we are back into how people act, when they're going to the
מקוה. mikvah. They're going to the מקוה mikvah before sunset. Because although
they don't become fully purified until the stars come out, they have
to go—the period from sunset till the stars come out is possibly
night, possibly day. So you have to go to the מקוה mikvah
before sunset and then you become pure when the stars come out.
So here it's assuming that they go to the מקוה mikvah pretty
soon right before sunset and that's when it begins, not at sunset,
not later, but right before sunset. Okay, רבי חנינא אומר, Rabbi Hanina
omer, רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina says, משעה שעני נכנס לאכול פיתו במלח,
mishashe ani nichnas lechol pito bemelach,
like we've seen before, when the poor person goes to eat the
bread with salt. רבי אחאי, Rabbi Achai, רבי אחאי Rabbi Achai says,
ואמרי לה רבי אחא אומר, veamrei lah Rabbi Acho omer, משעה שרוב
בני אדם נכנסים להסב. mishashe rov bnei adam nichnasin lehasev. When the
majority of people, you know, the majority of society, let's say middle-class
whatever, when they enter into the house in order to recline. Not
to sit down, you know, this is sort of the Roman context
that you would eat, you'd be, you know, on those reclining beds
like we talk about for פסח, Pesach, that reclining. And this presumably,
if you're going to eat a nice meal being reclined, that's going
to be not as soon as the sunset, that's going to be
done a little bit later into the evening with preparation and so
on. So that's when you do it. Interesting also again that picture
all of a sudden. You know, if you're not an עני, ani,
every day you're going into your house and you're reclining when you're
eating a meal. We don't tend to think about that, but that's
what we're finding out right now. And again, the question of like
who is serving as the model is an excellent point. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואי אמרת, veee amart, if you
say, עני וכהן חד שיעורא הוא, ani vekohen chad shiura hu, when
עני ani and a כהן kohen are the same time, so רבי
חנינא היינו רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Hanina haynu Rabbi Yehoshua. So רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina said
when the עני ani eats—when the poor person eats the bread
and salt, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said when the כהנים kohanim
are able to eat their תרומה, truma, and they seem to be
arguing. אלא לאו שמע מינה, ella lav shema mina, you must hear
from this, שיעורא דעני לחוד ושיעורא דכהן לחוד, shiura deani lechud veshiura
dekohen lechud, that they are—that those are different times. שמע מינה. shema
mina. Okay, that is a very good point. We do know that
these are different times. Again, what is fascinating here is you never
get this anywhere else, like those tiny little, you know, gradations of
this minute, that minute, five minutes before, ten minutes after. Normally we
have a couple of times: day and night. Maybe we have the
period of בין השמשות. bein hashmashot. Okay, and that's if you're working
on a night and day model, but if you're working on a
בשכבך ובקומך, beshochbecha uvekumecha, you get pulled into the realities of daily
life and you could have a lot of possible, you know, different
times to frame it.
רבי אחאי Rabbi Achai says משעה שרוב בני אדם נכנסים להסב. mishashe
rov bnei adam nichnasin lehasev. So we have כהנים, kohanim, we have
עניים, aniim, we have בני אדם.
bnei adam. Right, all three different times. Before we said at least
two of them were the same. No, we didn't say they have
to be, we said they might be. Two could be, all three
could not be the same. Now we're finding out that none of
them are. אמר מר, amar mar, so now just to wrap this
up, אמר ליה רבי יהודה, amar leh Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda said back to—oh, did I skip that line? I'm sorry, I
skipped the line right there at the bottom. Okay, we'll go read
it back in the משנה Mishnah then we'll go back here. רבי
מאיר אומר משעה שהכהנים טובלים לאכול בתרומתן. Rabbi Meir omer mishashe hakohanim
tovlin lechol betrumatan. If I ever do that again, correct me. אמר
לו רבי יהודה, amar lo Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said,
והלא כהנים מבעוד יום טובלים. vehalo kohanim mibeod yom tovlin. How can
you say that when they go to the מקוה? mikvah? That's before
sunset and of course that wouldn't be presumably time when people go
to bed. How could you—how could you do it in the middle
of the day, especially if your model is night versus day? You
can't do it before sunset, that's daytime, that's not nighttime. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר מר, amar mar, אמר ליה רבי יהודה, amar
leh Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said— ולאו כהני מבואי יומא
טובלין? v'lav kani miboei yoma tovlin? How can you say that that
when they go to the מקוה, mikvah, that's before, that's while it's
still the previous day? שפיר קאמר ליה רבי יהודה לרבי מאיר, Shapir
ka'amar lei Rabi Yehuda l'Rabi Meir, that's really a good point that
he's saying to him, what would רבי מאיר Rabi Meir say back?
For רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka'amar lei. Here's
how רבי מאיר Rabi Meir would answer back: מי סברת דאנא אבין
השמשות דידך קאמינא? Mi savarta d'ana a'bein hashmashos didach ka'amina? What makes
you think that I'm referring to prior to your בין השמשות? bein
hashmashos? רבי יהודה's Rabi Yehuda בין השמשות bein hashmashos was we find
out in שבת Shabbos from the time the sun sets till the
stars come out, roughly about fifteen minutes, thirteen and a half minutes
or so, which we'll discuss another time how that translates into what
we do today. But prior to his בין השמשות bein hashmashos is
before the sun sets. So רבי מאיר Rabi Meir says, I'm not
talking about prior to your בין השמשות bein hashmashos before the sun
sets. אנא אבין השמשות דרבי יוסי קאמינא. Ana a'bein hashmashos d'Rabi Yosi
ka'amina. I'm going on רבי יוסי's Rabi Yosi בין השמשות. bein hashmashos.
רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi says בין השמשות bein hashmashos is a split
second and it occurs right before the stars come out. So according
to רבי יוסי, Rabi Yosi,
you've got this whole part of...
Oh, I'm sorry, I did, see, I did it again. I'm so
eager to end. Okay, okay, thank you. Four lines, five lines before
the line get wide, I'm sorry. הי מינייהו מאוחר? Hai minaihu me'uchar?
So after having said that, thank you, after having said that the
עני ani and the כהן kohen are different times, which time is
later? מסתברא דעני מאוחר. Mistabra d'ani me'uchar. It makes sense that the
עני ani eats his bread later than the כהנים, kohanim, which means
later than the stars coming out. That's pretty interesting. But if you're
an עני, ani, you're working pretty much, you're working longer. So he
goes even later than the stars come out. דאי אמרת דעני מוקדם,
D'ei amart d'ani mukdam, because if an עני ani is earlier, רבי
חנינא היינו רבי אליעזר. Rabi Chanina hainu Rabi Eliezer.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to understand that there's a million
different possible times. So if the עני ani would be before the
stars come
out, then that would essentially put us in the רבי אליעזר Rabi
Eliezer time, because רבי אליעזר's Rabi Eliezer time
is משישקע החמה, misheyishka hachama, right, is sunset. So if we're going
prior to צאת, Tzeis, the next time we would hit
would be sunset. We don't want to assume that there's a little
slice between sunset and when the stars come out. So that can't
be because that would then just conflate it with רבי אליעזר. Rabi
Eliezer. אלא לאו שמע מינה, Ela lav shma mina, so here you
see דעני מאוחר, d'ani me'uchar, that the עני's ani time must be
even later. And as we said, that certainly makes a lot of
sense. שמע מינה, Shma mina, you do see that. Now back to
what we were saying before. אמר ליה רבי יהודה ולאו כהני מבואי
יומא טובלין? Amar lei Rabi Yehuda v'lav kani miboei yoma tovlin?
Don't they go the day before? How can you say, רבי יהודה,
Rabi Yehuda, that they do it before when they go to the
מקוה? mikvah? That's the prior day. שפיר קאמר ליה רבי יהודה לרבי
מאיר. Shapir ka'amar lei Rabi Yehuda l'Rabi Meir. That's a good point.
For רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir, הכי קאמר
ליה. hachi ka'amar lei. Here's what he would say: מי סברת דאנא
אבין השמשות דידך קאמינא? Mi savarta d'ana a'bein hashmashos didach ka'amina? What
makes you think I'm talking about your בין השמשות bein hashmashos that
begins at sunset? אנא אבין השמשות דרבי יוסי קאמינא. Ana a'bein hashmashos
d'Rabi Yosi ka'amina. I'm talking about the בין השמשות bein hashmashos of
רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi that begins only a second before the stars
come out. דאמר רבי יוסי בין השמשות כהרף עין. D'amar Rabi Yosi
bein hashmashos keheref ayin. רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi says בין השמשות bein
hashmashos is like the blinking of an
eye. זה נכנס וזה יוצא ואי אפשר לעמוד עליו. Ze nichnas v'ze
yotzei v'i efshar la'amod alav. One goes in and one comes out
and it's impossible to exactly determine that split second. So therefore, I
am saying after sunset but it's before בין השמשות bein hashmashos because
it's רבי יוסי's Rabi Yosi בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. Again interesting, it
doesn't bother, it's still הלכתית halachically day. If בין השמשות bein hashmashos
only starts
a second before צאת, Tzeis, הלכתית halachically you're still, it's still day.
But since in reality it's after the sun sets, it doesn't bother
us that the time of שמע Shema would begin when it's הלכתית
halachically day. What bothers us is that the time of שמע Shema
would begin when the night שמע Shema would begin, you know, the
going to sleep שמע Shema would begin when the sun is still
up over the earth. So again, it's the issue, it's not necessarily
הלכתית halachically day and night. You could even begin the night שמע
Shema when it's still הלכתית halachically day as long as the sun
has set, and that is what רבי מאיר Rabi Meir is saying.
And I will just, I know we're over or whatever, but I'm
just going to finish this so we can start with something new
tomorrow. קשיא דרבי מאיר דרבי מאיר. Kashya d'Rabi Meir d'Rabi Meir. If
you look, רבי מאיר Rabi Meir in one place, you know, the
two רבי מאירs Rabi Meir we quoted in the various ברייתות braisos
or whatever don't agree with one another. I'll leave it to you
to unpack
that. So תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי מאיר. Trei tannai aliba d'Rabi Meir.
Fine, there are two versions about what רבי מאיר's Rabi Meir position
is and they're reflected in these different things. קשיא דרבי אליעזר דרבי
אליעזר. Kashya d'Rabi Eliezer d'Rabi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer in the
ברייתא braisa is not the רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer on משנה. Mishna.
Again, you look, you'll see they're different times. תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי
אליעזר. Trei tannai aliba d'Rabi Eliezer. Fine, there are two traditions about
what רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer said. ואי בעית אימא רישא לאו דרבי
אליעזר היא. V'i ba'is eima reisha lav d'Rabi Eliezer hi. The beginning
of the משנה, Mishna, רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer only emphasized when it
ends. It ends at the end of the first אשמורה. ashmura. The
משנה Mishna when it said when it begins, when the כהנים kohanim
eat their תרומה, terumah, that wasn't necessarily part of רבי אליעזר's Rabi
Eliezer statement. Okay.